let's find the derivative of tangent 3x
using the first principle's definition
of derivatives we'll start by defining
our function f ofx = tangent 3x the
definition of a derivative states that F
Prime of x equals the limit as H
approaches Z of f of x + H - F ofx all
over H when we substitute our function
we get the limit as H approaches is 0 of
tangent of 3 * x + H - tangent of 3x all
over H next we'll convert the tangent
functions to S over cosine this gives us
the limit as H approaches 0 of sin of 3x
+ H over cosine of 3x +
hus s of 3x over cosine of 3x all over H
to subtract these fractions we need a
common denominator
multiplying the numerator and
denominator of each fraction by the
denominator of the other fraction gives
us this expression the numerator is in
the form of the sign difference formula
this simplifies to S of 3 H in the
numerator now we can factor out a three
from the S term giving us 3 * s of 3 H
over 3 H ided by the product of the
cosiness as H approaches 0
s of 3 H over 3 H approaches 1 and
cosine of 3x + H approaches cosine of 3x
this gives us 3 over cosine 2 3x which
equal 3 secant 2 of 3x therefore we have
shown that the derivative of tangent of
3x = 3 secant 3x